<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd">
<book id="top-of-user-guide">
  <bookinfo>
    <title>Grotag User Guide</title>

    <keywordset>
      <keyword>Amigaguide</keyword>

      <keyword>convert</keyword>

      <keyword>pretty print</keyword>

      <keyword>DocBook</keyword>

      <keyword>HTML</keyword>
    </keywordset>

    <copyright>
      <year>2008</year>

      <holder>Thomas Aglassinger</holder>
    </copyright>

    <legalnotice>
      <para>Permission is granted to copy, distribute and/or modify this
      document under the terms of the GNU Free Documentation License, Version
      1.2 or any later version published by the Free Software Foundation; with
      no Invariant Sections, no Front-Cover Texts, and no Back-Cover Texts. A
      copy of the license is included in the section entitled "GNU Free
      Documentation License".</para>
    </legalnotice>

    <releaseinfo>$Revision$</releaseinfo>

    <author>
      <firstname>Thomas</firstname>

      <surname>Aglassinger</surname>
    </author>
  </bookinfo>

  <preface id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>Amigaguide is a file format and application for AmigaOS. It enables
    to author and view hypertext documentation to some extend comparable to
    HTML or WinHelp. Most of the online documentation written for Amiga
    applications or about developing Amiga applications uses Amigaguide.
    Outside of AmigaOS however Amigaguide is unused and consequently hardly
    any viewers exist.</para>

    <para>Altough most Amigaguide documents are useless without access to an
    Amiga (real or emulated), occasionally a need arises to read such
    documentation on other platforms. Grotag is designed to address this need.
    It allows to convert Amigaguide documents to the platform independent HTML
    format, for which viewers exist on any reasonably modern system.
    Furthermore you can convert to DocBook, a format popular for technical
    documentations, allowing to bring along existing manuals into the 21st
    century for further editing.</para>

    <para>Grotag is written in Java (version 1.5 or later), which is supported
    by many current platforms such as Mac OS X (version 10.5 or later),
    Windows and Linux to name just a few.</para>

    <para>To find out what is new in this version, see the <link
    linkend="changes">revision history</link>. For updates and support, visit
    the Grotag homepage at <ulink
    url="http://grotag.sourceforge.net/">http://grotag.sourceforge.net</ulink>.</para>
  </preface>

  <chapter id="installation">
    <title>Installation</title>

    <section id="download">
      <title>Download</title>

      <para>...</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="command-line-usage">
    <title>Command line usage</title>

    <section id="command-line-launch">
      <title>Launch Grotag</title>

      <para>To launch Grotag from the command line, open a terminal window
      (console) and enter:</para>

      <para><userinput>java -jar .../path/to/Grotag.jar
      --help</userinput></para>

      <para>Replace "<filename>.../path/to/</filename>" by the location of the
      folder you extracted <filename>Grotag.zip</filename> to and where
      <filename>Grotag.jar</filename> is located.</para>

      <para>As a result, you should see a short decription of the options you
      can pass to Grotag. Don't worry about them now, all of them will be
      explained later in this chapter.</para>

      <para>Because it is somewhat boring to type that much each time you want
      to launch Grotag, it is recommended to define a console alias. In bash,
      simply enter:</para>

      <para><userinput>alias grotag="java -jar
      .../path/to/Grotag.jar"</userinput></para>

      <para>After that, you can simply run</para>

      <para><userinput>grotag --help</userinput></para>

      <para>to get same result as before. To avoid having to retype the alias
      each time you open a new terminal, add it to the shell startup file
      (<filename>~/.bashrc</filename> or <filename>~/.profile</filename>
      depending on your platform.)</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Showing help and other information</title>

      <para>To read a short description of all options available for Grotag,
      run:</para>

      <para><userinput>grotag --help</userinput></para>

      <para>To learn which version of Grotag you are using, run:</para>

      <para><userinput>grotag --version</userinput></para>

      <para>To obtain information about Grotag's license, run:</para>

      <para><userinput>grotag --license</userinput></para>
    </section>

    <section id="command-line-validate">
      <title>Validate Amigaguide documents</title>

      <para>To validate an Amigaguide document named
      <filename>some.guide</filename>, run:</para>

      <para><userinput>grotag --validate some.guide</userinput></para>

      <para>In case Grotag detects any inconsistencies, it will report what it
      would have done in order to fix them. This isn't necessarily what you
      would have done to fix them, but still shows exactly where something is
      wrong.</para>

      <para>If you trust Grotag to do the right thing, you can let it fix the
      reported issues by using the command line option
      <userinput>--pretty</userinput>.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="command-line-pretty">
      <title>Pretty print and fix Amigaguide documents</title>

      <para>Amigaguide never came with an authoring tool or a formal
      specification of the format. Consequently many existing Amigaguide
      documents contain little inconsistencies the rather lenient Amigaguide
      application stilled displayed without any trouble.</para>

      <para>Grotag takes a different approach: it points even tiny little
      errors, and makes an attempt to fix it in a way that preserves the
      content while resulting in an documents that does not have the issue
      anymore.</para>

      <para>Furthermore Grotag cleans up formatting and upper/lower case in
      mark up.</para>

      <warning>
        <para>Note that the original version of the Amigaguide document will
        be overwritten and consequently be lost unless you made a backup copy
        of it before applying <userinput>--pretty</userinput>.</para>
      </warning>

      <para>In order to clean up the file <filename>ugly.guide</filename>,
      run:</para>

      <para><userinput>grotag --pretty ugly.guide</userinput></para>

      <para>In case you want to clean up multiple files, you can pass all of
      them along at once.</para>
    </section>

    <section id="command-line-docbook">
      <title>Convert Amigaguide documents to DocBook XML</title>

      <para>To convert an Amigaguide document named
      <filename>some.guide</filename> to a DocBook XML file named
      <filename>some.xml</filename>, run:</para>

      <para><userinput>grotag --docbook some.guide</userinput></para>

      <para>To use a different name for the output file, specify a second
      file. For example, to store the DocBook version of
      <filename>some.guide</filename> in <filename>other.xml</filename>,
      run:</para>

      <para><userinput>grotag --docbook some.guide
      other.xml</userinput></para>

      <para>The DocBook output does not preserve any formatting command like
      <code>@{b}</code>, <code>@{fg shine}</code> and so in. It only
      reproduces the structure of the document. Each guide represents a
      chapter, and each node is a section. If the Amigaguide document
      specified in the command line links to other documents, they will be
      included in the DocBook output as additional chapters.</para>
    </section>
  </chapter>

  <chapter id="changes">
    <title>Changes</title>

    <para>This chapter describes improvements compared to earlier versions of
    Grotag.</para>

    <section id="v0.0">
      <title>Version 0.0, xx-Aug-2008</title>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Initial release.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
  </chapter>
</book>
